you so in the last lecture we looked at ah
some of the basic processes of cognitive psychology
we looked at what cognitive psychology is
composed of we looked at the schools which
led to the development of cognitive psychology
is a field we look at the subject matter of
cognitive psychology in terms of mental representations
what are mental representations what do they
represent how do they combine together to
find knowledge and how mental representations
are manipulated the way they can be expressed
the way they can be understood
in this lecture we look at why brain is to
be brought into the idea of cognitive psychology
up till now we have been looking at mental
processes and we have been looking at mental
representations and the functions of mental
representations we are looking at how mental
representations function
but the idea of cognitive psychology in terms
of what behavior is said or in terms of what
cognitive is said proposed that mental representations
explain functions the process of how they
combine together explain functions of a of
how mental activities take place is not enough
so at the inception of cognitive psychology
it was all about the functional aspect of
how mental representations make up mental
activity and mental knowledge
now one of the co challenges one of the main
challenges of cognitive psychology is to understand
what happens in the mind and how does the
mind does what it does the conception of the
mind have been differently put by different
people philosophers have given one way of
what mind is psychologists have understood
mind in more in terms of consciousness understanding
consciousness and the go through the cognitive
revolution the understanding of the mind ah
was put down to or brought down to the understanding
of mental representations understanding mental
processes mentally ah activities and so on
and so forth
up till now till the cognitive revolution
the study of mental processes the the study
of mental activity the study of cognition
which is basically the study of mental activities
was in terms of functions but the mind cannot
work on its own and so it it is the the idea
of mind and brain as a computer hardware and
software introduces first the first time brain
as the act system on which the mind works
and so one of the most interesting fact that
has been bought or that has been thought of
as by cognitive psychologists is introduction
of the brain in the whole idea of study of
mental processes of how mental events takes
place
the question is why do we study the brain
what help will we get looking at the brain
it is composed of different neurons neural
grooves and these neural grooves have biological
structure and so at the sight of it it does
not appeal or it does not ah give us much
information about mental processes or the
functioning of the mind
so why should we actually look at the brain
looking at the brain will help us identify
those processes and the correct combination
of processes that are required to complete
a task what does that mean what it would mean
is that since the brain leads to the mind
the working of the mind the process of the
mind will have a direct impact or would directly
project to the brain and so changes in brain
structure changes in brain activity can then
be correlated to the of the mind think of
it in this way and this is a very ah blow
not example
suppose a region a of the brain activates
when a certain mental processes takes place
and it does not activate it does not show
activity when a certain b mental process takes
place then now we have an observable a quantifiable
fact or a quantifiable system on which we
can look at changes because these brain activities
the the increase and decrease of brain activities
will signal whether process a is working or
whether process b is working
and so one of the ah reasons of including
the brain or bringing up the brain into the
whole idea of study of cognitive psychology
is to identify because brain helps us in identifying
what mental processes are taking place if
we are able to form correlations between mental
activity and brain activity but then there
is a catch to it what is the catch different
information processes they lead to the same
kind of mental experience
what i am trying to tell you here think of
emotions now there is a correlation between
a brain region which is the amygdala and the
kind of emotion that people have and so if
i am looking at an happy emotion or if i am
looking at positive emotion what will happen
is that most on most positive emotions the
same or nearly same brain regions will actually
activate or show activity
so how do i go ahead and pinpoint those brain
networks which lead to the happiness or sadness
factor also there is no way to tell us how
does the brain did use or give labels to these
emotions whether this is excited this is happy
and this activity leads to this kind of emotional
ah feeling
so then the different sort of information
processes can produce similar results or can
produce similar kind of act as in ah in outputs
is one of the basic problems by including
of including the brain so one of the problems
is that also there is a problem which is called
the structure process trade off why does it
mean this is the same thing that i was trying
to explain you a little while ago what is
the structure process trade off i try to explain
this to you in a very easy way saul stonberg
sternberg sorry was trying to identify how
people search mentally what is the process
people use for doing mental search and for
that he gave people students volunteers experiments
so the in the first conceptualization what
sternberg was trying to do
was trying to find out how information is
accessed from memory any conceptualized so
an experiment which he gave to volunteers
the experiment was like this
certain numbers were given to people for example
numbers one three five seven and nine and
nine and later on these people once these
numbers were shown to them later on these
numbers were shown to them one by one and
they were asked to tell with confidence whether
these numbers were in the list or not so it
is like a list recognition
so what happens in this experiment is this
list of number was given to people to remember
to learn and once the learning was over one
by one these numbers are presented and they
were asked to decide they were asked to recognize
whether each of these numbers represent in
the list or not what he conceptualized is
that this kind of list excess memory excess
happens through serial search and why did
he ah why did he propose that he found out
that as the list increases the verification
time also increases so list increases the
length of the list increases the verification
time also increases
what he found out from his studies well that
information excess from memory was in a serial
way so what happens is that when once you
show this list to people people formed a mental
image of this and then later on when you show
one of these members of the list and ask them
to verify from their mental image or from
the mental representation whether this is
present or not we what people tend to do is
match this with this if the match of this
with this results in a yes response the search
is terminated
if it is not you get a negative response here
and so the search goes to the next item whether
this and these are similar it is not so search
goes to the third item not match again not
match again not match the list returns to
the first item verifies it again and then
gives an output saying that it was not present
in the list and this is a serial search so
what happens is one item at the same time
list two is matched to the list and that gives
this kind of a serial search system
and so obviously as the number of items will
increase the verification time will increase
because this serial searches have to be more
in number this was what saul sternberg proposed
and this is how what he said is the reason
for accessing or how information is accessing
memory but later on people like townsend gave
a different conceptualization of information
accessing from memory what did townsend say
townsend said that the the same conceptualization
that i have the same problem can i that i
have can be thought of as balls
in a plate and so now i have one three seven
four and nine
and instead of a serial search what really
happens is information is searched through
parallel processes information access from
memory is done through parallel processes
now if that is true if parallel processes
occur in the memory then adding new items
into this list for example two and eight should
not increase the time of verification as list
length increases this is not what was found
what townsend found that as the number of
balls the number of item increases the time
of verification also increases
so how do i confer it for a serial search
it was accounted in terms of the fact that
more number of processes are there and more
structure is in so as the number of processes
increases oh sorry the number of searches
increases the time will increase but in this
case when i have parallel searches here the
same structure in the same structure the number
of items are there but still the time of verification
increases how do i confer this
they counting further this is done in terms
of the number of processes that take place
what happens is in serial search
although the process of verification is single
but the structure that stores this information
is a bigger structure and so what happens
is although the process is a single process
since the structure is more or there is a
bigger structure which stores this information
the time of verification will increase because
as i add up more items into it more structure
is required
on the other hand parallel search
although the structure is same but the number
of processes that are there the number of
comparisons that have to should be done the
number of processes takes up for the or accounts
for the more time what will happen is since
there are lets let us assume that there are
four process processes which run in parallel
what will happen is these four processes will
have to do multiple evaluations and these
multiple evaluations although this is much
faster but these multiple evaluations are
the reason for the increase in verification
time and so the inclusion of the brain the
inclusion of the idea of the brain gives us
a chance to identify what is the reason for
the mental ah activity or what is the reason
how this mental activity is taking place
another interesting thing is the idiocracy
theory is the requirement of idiocracy what
does it say the inclusion of the brain into
the understanding of mental processing or
mental processes gives us this chance to understand
what necessary or what adequate processes
or what requirements are there for certain
mental process to take place what does this
mean it means that if four different processes
or if four different answers of a particular
way a particular process through which a mental
experiences felt is being proposed given the
structural constraint of the brain which of
them will be the most correct what do i mean
by this
in the first part i have explained that multiple
processes will give the same result but how
do i go ahead and look at which of this is
the most optimal or which of this is the most
optimal theory the best theories or best thought
of theories because there will be several
theories there will be several reasons of
how the mental process appear and so what
the idiocracy laws will tell us is that given
the constraints of the brain given the constraints
of what the brain has or what structures of
the brain are which of the theory explains
the processing or the answer to a mental process
or the output to a mental process
and so idiocracy laws says that brain inclusion
of the brain will help us in pinpointing which
theory works in which theory does not and
what should be done for theories or what changes
could be done in a theory to adjust it so
that it explains a menl mental phenomena
now there are certain paradigms to the study
of cognitive psychology first of all let us
understand what a paradigm is it is a body
of knowledge structured according to what
is proponents consider important and what
they do not so it is basically what should
be the basic idea behind cognitive psychology
or what what is the ah basic matter behind
cognitive psychology and so this these paradigms
are assumptions which are made by investigators
appropriate types of research methods because
these paradigms then when i use a particular
paradigm when i use a particular approach
to study cognitive psychology it will not
only give leaders to having a set of assumptions
which vary across paradigms but it also gave
us different methods of research of the same
different processes or the same mental process
it will also give new questions in the field
so the same processes same mental process
or same mental activities if it is studied
by different paradigms if it is studied by
different approaches not only will it give
us different types of research methods of
having same process but it would also give
us new questions and also new analog is to
it or new ah similar problems to it of how
the solutions can be generated and so in cognitive
psychology there are four basic paradigm that
i wish to make you aware of here
the first paradigm is called the information
processing approach and so this approach started
with the cognitive revolution the part of
this approach this approach comes from the
structure list and what this approach says
is that cognition is basically information
passing through a system so there are several
systems out there seres several ah process
systems in in the mind and these process systems
takes in information from a previous process
a processing system and passes processes it
in certain way and passes it along to the
next system
and so information processing approach says
that cognitive psychology the subject matter
of cognitive psychology should be how how
these systems process information the basic
information processing approach is built in
this way it says that any information which
comes out or which people encounter from the
environment is first detected so this is the
environment and this environment provides
certain signals or certain kind of information
and this information is detected by the mind
or by the brain using a process called attention
this attention then separates the different
formats of information which are passed on
from the environment so the information which
is passed on from the environment could be
in visual medium it could be an auditory medium
or it could mean olfactory medium or the other
two senses which is heptic or the taste gustatory
once these different formats or this different
types of information is detected by the human
system through process of ah attention it
is passed on to something called a short term
memory and what is short term memory its a
system or its a place where information which
is taken in through a process of perception
using attention is thrown here or is put here
for storage now this storage system is a temporary
storage and so if people do not rehearse this
information do not go ahead and repeat this
information it is lost here through forgetting
if it is rehearsed it goes back to something
called long term memory also information which
is coming out from the environment is first
recognized through perception so perception
has certain filters and these filters are
three these basic modules will recognize different
information which is coming from the environment
i am talking about here the content so based
on the content the information is stored in
short term memory from the short term memory
it is rehearsed it goes to long term memory
once the information comes into long term
memory this is basically categorized into
already so existing information ah systems
or information places in the long term memory
so mostly long term memory has a very categorical
structure
since long term memory has a lot of information
to into it so what it does is it categorizes
information
into different categories what are these categories
these categories are generally formed through
something called schema if it is episodic
knowledge or it if it is semantic knowledge
this categorization is done through something
called hierarchical tree structure what you
need to understand here is that this long
term memory takes in information from short
term memory and it binds this information
which is coming from short term memory into
already existing long term memory information
for example the next time you see an apple
you do not need to learn that this is an apple
what happens is when an apple is presented
to you this apple is perceived by your perceptual
system the perceptual system identifies a
scale color shape and these kind of informations
texture passes on to short term memory the
short term memory takes this information ask
the long term memory in terms of given the
fact that this is the format and this is the
meaning or this is the kind of information
that is coming from this structure or this
mental representation what could could be
the long term memory then compares this information
and tells you that this is an apple
or if tomorrow a black apple comes in now
when i taste it when i see it it looks like
an apple but the possibility of black apple
is not there so what the brain will do is
take this black colored apple compare it with
features which are existing in in the long
term memory and so since the black apple has
most of the features which is si similar to
any other apple only the color is different
so what will happen is this black apple now
gets stored up or gets included into the category
of apple which are already stored in long
term memory with one pointer to it or with
one exception to it saying that this is a
black color apple because most apples are
green and red in color so this is a unique
feature which says that it is black in color
so this is what the information processing
approach says it says that any information
comes in or it passes through certain stages
and these stages define how an information
or mental ah mental activity defines how an
information path is processed through this
system now the information processing approach
tells us about the systems the processes and
the goals what is the systems here the various
systems which help in the processing of information
are the sensory memory here the short term
memory here the long term memory here what
are the processes which help us in in understanding
this mental experience or in sending mental
activity our processes recognition rehearsal
recording reorganization manipulation categorization
and so on and so forth and what are the goals
of it the goal is the response the goal is
the understanding
so in the apple example the processes which
help us and understanding the apple is the
short term memory the long term memory the
perceptual systems those are the processes
what are the sorry those are the structures
those are the systems the processes are the
process of encoding the process of recognition
the process of rehearsal the process of ah
ah response manipulation the process of identification
recognition these are the process through
which you identify this apple and the response
the output is storage of a new kind of apple
the response output is the information the
knowledge that a black apple also exists this
is the goal though the goal is to understand
that that can only be cal can also be black
is achieved through a system of processes
the second paradigm which has been used or
which is popular in cognitive psychology is
connectivism what is connectivism now connectivism
is also known as parallel distributed processing
model and what it says is that there are several
small units which are connected together and
these connections lead to the formation of
mental experience
in the information processing approach we
saw certain systems interacting with certain
processes to give a particular kind of a goal
in connectionism what happens is there are
several small units and these small units
connect to each other through certle connect
connections and these connections later on
lead to the formation of mental experience
how does this connectionism works
the basic fundamental premise of this connectionism
theory is that individual neurons in the brain
they do not transmit large amounts of symbolic
information but instead they compute or they
come up with the goal by being appropriately
connected to large number of situational units
so what is the meaning of this it means that
there are specialized systems and these specialized
systems are connected to each other and these
connections lead to the idea of mental process
for example lets
understand how this particular sentence robin
is a bird the mental experience to this is
explained by connectionism look at robin this
is our name it is a kind of bird and so if
you look on this side of it it falls from
the category of birds so there are robin a
canary sunfish salomon all these are birds
and these fall under the living things living
things have ah are further divided into plants
and animal then into trees and flowers bird
fish and so on and so forth so basically on
this side you have a system of connections
through which in which you have categorization
in terms of living nonliving birds animals
and so on and so forth and so robin forms
robin goes here the name robin goes here
is or is a is basically a connector which
defines what is the relation of robin to the
word bird and once robin which is a bird is
connected to three to this connection of is
a we can then say that if the mental experience
of robin is a bird can then conclude or can
give then can give us the idea that since
robin is a bird it should have wings it should
be able to fly why because the idea that bird
falls under the category of living things
and living things certain features of living
things are there and these live certain features
should be present on any member of living
things
so bird is a member of living things and so
everything that is there in the living thing
should be present in bird so robin should
robin which is basically a bird should be
living should be locomoting should be ah doing
daily activities and certain features of the
bird should also be present in them
the basic idea and connection is is that it
is not big processes it is not big systems
and process the connection between big processes
and systems which leads to the formation of
mental ah activity or mental experience but
there are several connections between several
networks which are there there as there is
a network of what a bird looks like there
is a network of what if there is a bird what
is the basic feature of the bird and so on
and so forth and this is how connections are
so small units small amount of units or small
units combine together to give us the mental
experience now these units which combine with
each other to give us the kind of experience
that trees where that we get when we talk
about robbing is a bird it they have certain
weights and so weight wise combination will
tell us what features should robin have
now we will discuss connectionism the idea
of connectionism in detail in the chapter
of memory where we look into ah what is semantic
memory and what is the parallel distributing
model there and how symbolic ah the hierarchy
structure of symbolic memory is and those
things there but the basic difference between
connectionism and information processing approaches
in information processing approach there is
one system there is a set of there is a set
of system and set of processes which leads
to the goal but whereas in connectionism several
units several independent units they combined
together to give us the mental experience
the third approach to studying of cognitive
psychology is called the evolutionary approach
now what this approach does it says that the
study of mental processes through the ways
in which the i p model the information processing
model and connectivism connectivist models
look at they basically do not count for evolutionary
features or evolutionary approaches evolutionary
inputs to our understanding of cognitive psychology
so what they say is cognitive psych subjective
matter of cognitive psychology is not how
mental processes are studying off mental process
how mental process a process but there are
certain specialized competence which comes
through evolutionary input for example basic
cognitive abilities like language and three
dimensional perception of perception of depth
are present in very small children and they
do not need some kind of mental experience
for them to develop that
and so what evolutionary approach says that
human beings they have very specialized ideas
of completeness produced by our evolutionary
heritage evolution has a role to play in cognitive
psychology so the subject matter of cognitive
psychology the view the way of looking at
what cognitive psychology should study should
not only be the study of mental processes
and thoughts it should also be how evolution
has made us think in certain ways or behave
in certain ways
what they say the evolutionary approaches
say is that the human mind is basically a
biological system that has evolved over generations
and the development of the human mind has
come through a process of natural selection
so certain features or certain aspects certain
working of the human mind or the human brain
is inbuilt is evolutionary in nature and nature
has given us this ah kind of system to process
information
so basically then the evolutionary approach
will use evolutionary as one of the reason
of mental experience and one of the ah basic
views or one of the basic wa ways of looking
at how mental experiences are processed and
similar to that is the last approach which
is called the ecological approach the ecological
approach goes ahead and says that mental experiences
or cognition does not occur in isolation all
cognitive activities take place in certain
context and so contexts are very important
in studying cognition
so just studying the mental processes or what
is going in the brain what is going on in
the mind how the brain or what the brain does
or what mental experiences are what kind of
processes and systems make up certain kind
of ah ah certain kind of mental mental experience
should not be the only way of looking at cognition
of how cognition happens but one way of looking
at cognition or one viewpoint of looking at
cognition is also in terms of the ecology
or the culture in which people live because
culture has only a ah large role to play of
how information is processed certain cultures
do not allow information probe to be processed
in certain ways certain cultures allow information
to be cert certain ah process in certain ways
and that leads to the different kind of information
processing or different kind of thinking
think of the individualistic and the cult
and the collectivist culture the kind of culture
that the westerners have individualistic in
nature and the kind of culture that we have
here the asian countries have is more collectivist
nature and so the way the mental processes
the cognition of people who live in the west
are entirely different from the way we live
in our country because we have a collectivist
culture the reason is that from right on right
very beginning they the westerners are taught
to be individualistic taught to be alone taught
to be doing things on their own and so they
process information in an entirely different
way whereas the as in as asians since we live
in a collectivist culture what really happens
is the way we perceive information is always
in terms of how the whole society will look
into it
so basically then the clo ecological approach
says is that all collect cognitive activities
are shaped by the culture and context in which
they occur and so this brings an end to the
base the first section of where we looked
at the history of cognitive psychology the
subject matter of cognitive psychology the
various paradigms of cognitive psychology
of what it should be the what is the subject
matter what is the content what kind of things
are studied into it what kind of ah processes
are there and what is the input output kind
of a system this is the basic introduction
to the history of cognitive psychology
in upcoming lecture what we look into is how
do we study cognition now as i said cognition
is the mental process processing of mental
activities or mental representations so how
do we study this processing how do we study
this cognition in action is what we will do
in next lecture and from there on will slowly
move on to other cognitive processes or basic
cognitive processes such as perception things
like attention things like memory this decision
making and so on so forth
thank you