hello friends so we are back today continuing
from the last class where we studied what
is cognitive psychology and what is the subject
matter of cognitive psychology so in that
class earlier class we saw the basic ah subject
matter of cognitive psychology what are the
various inputs from various schools of psychology
to cognitive psychology what is it that we
study in cognitive psychology and the various
paradigms which are there for the study of
cognitive psychology how they explain mental
events and mental facts
in the last class we discussion cognition
is about understanding mental events and mental
facts ah how does mental processing take place
or mental events and how does the mind come
into play and what role the blame has in the
mind
in todays lecture we look at the various ways
of studying cognition what are the various
methods which are available for studying cognition
so let us begin
there from the start of cognitive psychology
and the or the of cognitive psychology there
were several methods which was out there to
study cognitive psychology the basic ah method
that primitive cognitive psychology or artificial
intelligence used didnt employ any role of
brain into it so the earlier the first advent
of cognitive psychology or the first ah wave
of cognitive psychology basically banked on
information processing theory
and so information processing theory was all
about mental processing how mental events
pro gets process to save ah several ah mental
mechanisms and what is the input what is the
output that kind of ah ah process or that
kind of structure was which have been studied
by cognitive psychology so information processing
theory as we saw in the last class actually
ah looks at the events and the mechanism frosting
mechanisms through which mental events or
mental ah activity is generated
in contrast artificial intelligence was ah
also looking at how at the process level mental
events are ah studied and both of these methods
did not play or did not emphasize the brain
in any ways as we know today that ah the mind
is actually ah a software or kind of a software
or mind is actually a a fact which is made
by the brain and so studying of the brain
is very important in studying ah cognitive
psychology
now some of the ah main reasons why the brain
should be included in the study of cognitive
ah psychology is to understand the dissociation
and association the process of dissociation
and associations because these dissociation
and associations will tell us what processes
are similar if two mental acts takes place
and what processes are different if in two
mental events or two mental process ah acts
to the heart of this debate is the idea of
localizing those brain areas to finding out
those brain areas which act up which show
activity when a particular cognitive act ah
a particular cognitive process is initiated
and so what the new da ah cognitive psychology
or the new field of cognitive psychology is
looking at not only the information processing
or the artificial intelligence approach where
mental process events and ah various other
ah mental events are studied but in relation
to it the new wave of cognitive psychology
is also looking at brain areas of how brain
areas or what brain areas are really ah involved
in producing cognition
there are multiple methods of studying cognitive
psychology as i said and so each of these
methods use a different measure a different
way to study cognition now these methods all
have their own problems and all have their
own limitations and what has to have what
to study to you to find out the complete method
or ah a perfect method to study cognition
would take into account the all these methods
why should we do that we should do that as
multiple methods when they provide information
what would happen is that the limitation of
one method could become the benefit of other
method and the benefit of what method could
serve as or could add up to more affording
information
and so when looking at multiple methods one
looking at multiple ways multiple ah ideas
or multiple approaches to studying cognition
this will give us a more complete picture
or a more desirable outcome of what cognition
is all about now the general goal of cognitive
psychology is to study dissociations and associations
at the level of the brain now when i say dissociation
and association what is it that i actually
mean
dissociation is a fact or a term which explains
that one if two processes or if two mental
acts give rise to activation in one area of
the brain how to we dissociate it simply stating
what it would really mean that an event if
an event or a variable leads to brain activation
during the processing of one task but doesnt
lead to the brain activation on the other
task this is what dissociation is
this will tell us which task requires that
particular mental activity or that particular
mental process and which of the task doesnt
require that particular mental task lets understand
with an example allen bradley developed the
idea of working membrane and so what bradly
said is that there is a whole conceptualization
of the central executive ah component of memory
which ha ah executes most of the ah working
process in in working memory and within the
central executive or with the central executive
or other parts of ah the working memory which
is ah the spatial store and the phonological
loop the idea of working memory is conceptualized
in this way that input or the encoding ah
from the environment is thrown into the central
executive which then assigns the audio input
the auditory input into the phonological loop
and the visual input into the spatial ah ah
and spatial loop or the spatial store what
does it mean
it means that at the level of processing itself
at the level of encoding itself or just after
encoding the mind takes away two inputs from
two difference senses and processes them separately
now the same region of the brain is involved
in storing the phonological ah ah ah loop
or the phonological matter and the spatial
matter is that true
so experiments are done to find out whether
this as the assigning of the visual ah input
and the auditory input into different stores
or the working memory whether they use the
same mental ah ah mental process or the same
brain areas and if different brain areas were
activated then we could say that both the
task the tasks of assigning the the auditory
input into the phonological loop and the visual
input into the spatial sketch pad they require
different brain areas and through this we
can then specifically study one of these areas
or deficit one of these areas
so allen bradley what he did was he did some
studies to find out what really happens at
the level of the brain so he specifically
inhabited or the visual input and he saw that
there was no ah ah deficit into the auditory
input what he did was he gave a visual task
to his subject and with this visual task he
actually loaded the working memory or ah the
attention the attention span with more ah
data more items and when that happen the subject
was not able the subject could not process
the vision input but the auditory input was
intact plus understand this in the more easy
example
so what allen bradley wanted to study is rather
if the visual input is loaded whether the
auditory input can function on its own meaning
which both the processes are both the processes
of visual input and the auditory input in
the working memory are ah have dissociative
processes or dissociative brain regions involved
into it
so in his task he gave ah visual task and
loaded the attention or loaded ah the central
executive with more visual information so
the subjects are not able to rehearse or not
able to ah study back the visual inputs but
the auditory input the auditory information
which was stored in phonological loop got
a proper rehearsal and so when the test was
done it was found out that although the subjects
are not able to correctly identify visual
ah items or visual matter auditory inputs
or auditory ah test or auditory inform information
retrieval was not at all disturbed
this particular ex experiment shows that dissociation
is at the core of studying cognition why because
dissociation can tell but tell us which processes
have similar although they have similar representations
but they use different mechanisms
similar to it is the study of associations
in associations what we actually study is
whether two different processes ah are linked
or two different processes actually excite
the same brain region for example in this
case ah experiments were done to find out
whether the frontal cortex the frontal regions
and ah another area of brain whether both
of them have anything to do with spatial representations
or ah ah of encoding of special ah into spatial
encodings
what they found out is that spatial information
when encoded through two different processes
or two different brain regions gave rise to
similar representations meaning which both
the brain processes or both the brain areas
although different but they combindly give
rise give rise to same interpretations
now why is the study of dissociation and association
important the study of dissociation and association
is important to find out which processes although
ah ah emanate from the same structure but
they lead to different task and which if two
different processes which emanate from different
brain areas converge on to a particular task
to find out the specificity to find out the
ah process through this
now the methods of studying cognition so there
are four different methods through which cognition
can be studied and so these methods are the
behavioral methods the correlation neural
method the causal method and the modeling
within the modeling we have the box model
approach and the neural network model of approach
so let us start with the behavioral methods
what the behavioral methods generally do is
they look at directly observable behavior
like reaction time the time when pa person
takes to react to something or accuracy of
how accurate a retrieval is from encoding
so these processes or these events responses
are map on to behavioral methods
the accuracy of response or the time taken
to response gives us an idea on to what behavioral
processes are going through in the processing
of a particular mental event now researchers
they attempt to draw inferences about what
kind of interpretations and what kind of processing
leads to the differences in accuracy and differences
in reaction time
four popular approaches that have been or
four popular methods within the behavioral
method has been used so what we will look
at is what is the beni what are the benefits
of each methods what are the drawbacks and
that kind of thing into less so lets go into
that comparison
as you can see the major behavioral methods
and methods used in cognitive psychology the
major methods are looking at the accuracy
of how accurate the retrieval is from the
encoding percentage of that is percentage
of correct responses response times judgments
and protocol
now lets take these methods one by one the
method of accuracy in this method of accuracy
a very good example to look at is item recall
or memory recall for item such as remembering
a particular job requirements or or a particular
task the advantage is this it gives an objective
idea of the processing effectiveness how effective
is the mental mechanism or the mental process
which is processing that particular event
the limit to accuracy method or behavioral
methods of accuracy is something called the
ceiling effect and floor effect
ceiling effect is when a task is made too
easy so that each person gets the highest
score and so it will be very difficult to
find out the exact processing mechanism similar
to this is the floor effect in which a task
is made so difficult that none of the pe people
are able to solve it and due to this will
not be able to a certain what processing mechanisms
are at play also they suffer from something
called speed accuracy trade of which means
that as it want to be more accurate on something
the more time it will it is going to take
as accuracy increases more accurate we want
the speed decreases or the time to perform
a task decreases is a inverse relationship
the second method here is response time which
is the time one takes to come up with a particular
response the advantage is this that it is
an objective method and suitable for measuring
of processing mechanisms that is at play and
also those unconscious processing mechanisms
now this the limitation to this method is
something called experimental expectancy effect
and task demands
what this really means is that each experimenter
when he is gets into an experiment he has
certain expectancy he has a certain want from
the subjects so this gets transferred to the
subjects subject identifies these expectancy
and actually behaves in a similar way so if
experiment of ones are subject to say yes
to most of the things or take more time in
responding what would really happen if the
subject understands that or judges that from
the from the experimenter and even if the
processing is fast they take more time
the third method is called the judgment method
here what really happens is to find out what
really ah what really is happening in or how
does particular process really work is people
are given a judgment scale and so there are
sev these are seven point or eight point nine
point scales which are given to people who
actually judge or go ahead and rate how they
are processing a particular item it is very
inexpensive to ah collect and it excesses
subjects reaction to a particular cognitive
process for example the thing like how are
you feeling right now and so test can be given
to people and what they could do is actually
go ahead and on a seven point scale go ahead
and tell on several questions or provide responses
to several questions as to how they are feeling
the problem with this method is that subjects
are not aware of how to use this scale and
so we get into difficulty the last of the
behavioral methods which i use to study cognition
is something called the protocol collection
the method here allows subject to verbally
announce what is going on or what they are
doing for example if i ask someone to go ahead
and show me how counting of two and three
is done
this person has to actually start the pa the
experiment the subject has to actually go
ahead and relate how his go how he is doing
the addition process for example thinking
of the number two thinking of the rule for
addition thinking of the number three going
adding carrying off and so on the protocol
method really ah uses or really requires the
subject to announce what is going on mentally
this method can tell you or the advantage
of this method is basically it can tell you
what are the steps basic steps through which
a mental processing happens or any task what
is the mental requirement for this task what
is the mental process for this task
for complex cognitive processes this cannot
obviously be used because people would not
be aware of what is going on and they could
not or they could not ac accurately go ahead
and describe what is being going on
the next method that we use in studying cognition
a cognitive processes is the correlation or
the neural methods now what does correlation
really mean or what is this what is the heart
of this method the heart of this method is
localization as we discussed at the start
of the lecture that the new way of a cognitive
science is looking up at the brain towards
the brain to explain how this cognitive processes
or mental events are being processed or how
is the mental event actually being processed
what is going on inside the mind what is going
on inside the subjects cognition how is the
processing input and output coming into effect
now there i explain to you that the brain
is a recent edition why because the brain
can objectively tell you the processing the
methods or by through which ah particular
mental event is being processed and so this
method looks at finding out or localizing
that area of the brain when a particular mental
event is being ah carried out what this method
does is actually tries to form a correlation
between the fact that when a mental event
happens which areas of the brain actually
show activity and so through correlation it
tries to show off or tries to ah find out
which area of the brain resp is responsible
through which kind of mental activity this
will benefit us as we will be able to specifically
now tell that ah each mental process or each
mental event or each mental mechanism is relate
to a particular brain area
the problem here could be that sometimes numerous
other brain areas beside the area of interest
also get excited and so it is it is a little
bit difficult or i would say a little challenging
to pinpoint the area that is responsible for
the core mental process which is being carried
out
another problem with this method is correlation
does not lead to causation correlation simply
means the two events by chance are related
to each other they do not mean that process
a leads to process b and so we cannot with
confidence say that this brain area excitation
of a particular brain area leads to a particular
mental event or particular mental process
or particular cognitive event
now there are couple of techniques which are
here so let us look at those techniques let
us look at the advantages of this techniques
and the disadvantages of the technique and
discuss how this method really works so the
causal neural methods have four different
techniques to look at i am sorry three different
techniques to look at and these ma techniques
are the neuro physiological studies the transcranial
magnetic stimulation and the drugs so i was
saying as i was seeing the correlation neural
methods the problems with the correlation
neural method so there are two problems with
this first that many areas side along or they
get along or an activated in addition to the
main area of interest and so what really happens
the problem with this method is to localize
the area of interest because the ma areas
also which inside along gets activated
and the second problem with the correlation
neural methods is that correlation not causing
causation now what really happens in correlation
is two events a and b they although show in
sink activity but correlation does not guarantee
that a is the cause of b or b is caused by
a and so there is no way to find out what
process leads to or what method leads to what
structural activation in terms of the brain
mind ah relations it would be very difficult
to find out whether the activation in area
deep to the mental processing or where the
mental processing leads to the activation
in an area
so there are four different methods here techniques
here to study the correlation or the correlational
localization of brain areas the first of these
technique is the e e g or the electroencephalograph
the electroencephalograph can also be used
for recording something called the e r b s
now what the e e g or the electroencephalograph
records are potentials from the scalp when
a particular mental activity takes place it
believed that a mental when a particular mental
activity takes place there are changes in
neuronal polarity and due to this a weak electrical
current actually passes to the scalp surface
the e e g senses which are placed in the scalp
at record these activities and based on that
are able to predict whether there is a activity
change from the baseline activity a baseline
activity is an activity when no mental processing
is being taking place and and ah when whenever
an activity takes place there will be a change
and so the changed activity subtracted from
the baseline activity will give you the kind
of mental activity if just being taken place
e e g s are also used for recording event
related potentials which are basically the
potentials which are recorded when a particular
stimulus is set and so after a particular
stimulus is initiated from there on to when
the response of the system or when the response
of a person takes place the e e g the ah the
electroencephalographic patterns of the brain
recorded and the time codes of this e e g
the time ah the changes in e e g from the
stimulus onset to the response is calculated
or recorded or studied and this gives us an
idea of what processes and what areas or what
kind of pattern of activity is being ah shown
by the brain
generally there are some very fixed patterns
ah that the brain show there is something
called the base activity that mostly happens
in everyday life is the alpha activity which
falls in the eight to thirteen hertz ah thirteen
cycle per second ah region then if as a person
gets more relaxed e the amplitude of these
waves increases and the frequency lowers down
when it comes back to something called delta
so on and so forth so as you get more worked
up as you are doing more general activity
the amplitude is less the frequency is more
and the banned pattern or the activity pattern
of the brain is generally in the eight to
fourteen hertz cycle per or cycle per second
region
an example of using e e g is to find out brain
patterns during sleep or something like ah
ah in terms or e r p something like p three
hundred now p three hundred is actually a
component which happens p three hundred is
when i say component what does it really mean
a component is a deviation in an electrical
activity which takes place wa after the start
of a event so when a stimulus is given ah
when a stimulus is initiated and the e e g
s are recorded three hundred milliseconds
after the stimulus ah stimulus initiated on
the positive direction if a peak is recorded
this is called the p three hundred
now the p three hundred generally the component
p three hundred generally is associated with
novelty so when the brain the the process
the mind looks at something which is noble
which is new it generates the p three hundred
activity and so these this this can be recorded
the spatial resolution of a e e g is very
poor because it cannot locate the area from
where or the neuronal group from where this
activity is being recorded as current passes
or current moves from the base of the brain
towards the surface of the brain it forms
a conical structure and so it loses most of
its strength and it is very ah difficult to
to go back in or to reverse engineer from
where the source of this activity is
although newer techniques do allow for something
called source localization from actually from
an e e g will pin point ah gross area of where
it is coming from
but generally speaking the e e g s have very
poor resolution in terms of temporal resolution
an e e g is excellent because it can show
you within within milliseconds of the activity
will within milliseconds of the mental event
the mental activity and can show a correlation
to that so in terms of time of processing
in terms of time course of processing of mental
events the e e g is very good can tell you
what events in in that on the time axis what
events process its a process or what even
processes take place that that kind of information
can be there gathered from an e e g
the invasiveness of this particular method
of the e e g is very low as you know have
to put anything inside the body the surface
senses actually captures the information and
so not much of an invasive process and the
cost for this particular method is very low
its smaller units are available in ah in ah
very few dollars you can buy them and start
using them
similar to the e e g is the m e g the magneto
encephalogram where electrical activity instead
of capturing the electrical activity the magnitive
activity is captured an example is detecting
activity from the auditory cortex ah different
picture stones
so here there are several sensors which are
put around ah the brain the magnetic activity
that is generated when a particular event
happens a particular stimulus ah after the
particular sti stimulus the particular event
which happens are ah recorded or the magnitive
activity of of which is generated by the neuronal
group which is processing the event are captured
through it
the special resolution of the magneto encephalograph
is very good it is up under one centimeter
in terms of temporal relation also it is very
good this is excellent the invasiveness since
we are not putting anything inside the body
it is very low and so invasiveness wise m
e g s are very good but the problem is buying
an m e g or establishing an m e g requires
a very high cost so cost too high it requires
ah ah system which produces this magnetic
moments or this prod produces magnetic fields
which actually are able to process or which
actually are able to record changes in brain
activity or neuronal activity when a particular
mental event is going on
third method that we use as a correlation
method or for localizing brain areas that
are responsible for a particular mental event
is the positron emission tomography the p
e t in cognitive psychology we ge we generally
use the fifteen o isotope the fifteen oxygen
isotope as a method for doing p e t so what
really happens is that the oxygen the fifteen
ah the o fifteen isotope which is radioactive
is injected with normal ah within the normal
body
and so this particular isotope is ah moving
around the body so when the brain does it
is believed that the when when the brain does
a particular function it pulls up more and
more ah blood and with the blood more and
more water also transports to the brain and
so when a particular at ah region of the brain
shows more fifteen the accumulation of more
fifteen isotope that is the region which is
ah correlated or which is assume to be active
in a particular process and this is how the
p e t or fifteen oxygen isotope is done
generally it is used to study or mostly it
is used to study language areas of the brain
of how the language areas process or what
is the processing that happens in language
area when we actually speak the special resolution
is very good up to one centimeter but the
temporal resolution is very poor because it
takes almost forty seconds to generate an
image out of ah the p e t of fifteen oxygen
ah isotope or the o fifteen isotope
invasiveness is high as we in ah as we inject
an isotope of oxygen which is radioactive
into the blood and so this has radioactive
properties which could ah lead to problems
although ah the kind of radioactivity that
happens with an oxy with o fifteen isotope
is as less as ah what a airline pilot would
actually get through in half a year of his
work so it is it is very ah very less but
still it is radioactive and so its best to
avoid it
on terms of the purchase cost it is a high
purchase cost because p e t need cyclotron
and p e t cameras and things for ah ah noticing
those senses which can go ahead and record
the radioactivity the low radioactivity of
this oxygen isotope so it is very costly in
that method and improvement on the p e t is
the m r i and the f m r i which was ah which
is a new addition to the study of the brain
or the brain processes or cognitive processes
the m r i on on one hand is actually stores
the structural integrity of how the structure
of the brain is the f m r i on the other hand
shows the blocks blood oxygen level depending
or how much oxygenated blood is taken up by
the brain when a particular activity is ah
being ah being processed by the brain
the m r i works on the principle of body magnets
or ah atoms of the ah of the body and how
they aligned to an external magnetic field
so what the m r i generally does it produces
a uniform magnetic field to which most atoms
of the body aligned and then radio ah ah pulse
is created or radio puls is it is generated
which disturbs the alignment of most atoms
of the ah of the area which is in the m r
i scan the speed of returning back is calculated
when when the magnets disaligned when the
particular pose
or the ah the particular elements in the in
the particular atoms of elements in the body
when radioisotope disaligns them from the
aligned ah from the ah alignment that the
m r i magnet does it returns back and the
speed with which the return back is calculated
and from there an image is generated and these
images or the speed at which the different
atoms get back or ah they come back is different
different media like bone ah skin or ah that
other issues in in in the body they have different
speeds of returning back or this is calculated
and an image is generated
in an f m r i what we really do is ah the
amount of ah oxygenated blood in comparison
to the deoxygenated blood at a particular
brain region which is processing a particular
event ah is taking that is calculated and
that gives us an idea of which region of the
brain is showing an activity through a sensor
the spatial resolution of an both the m r
i and f m r i is very superb it is very good
in the terms of millimeter inch the temporal
resolution is not that good but depends upon
ah the level of resolution that you want or
ah generally it is in terms of several seconds
so not like the e e g which can give you ah
the millisecond kind of a temporal resolution
but not as low as ah the p e t which gives
which takes almost forty seconds to produce
an image
so m r i s have decent time requirement or
this takes decent time to produce images the
invasiveness is low because m r i does not
ah the m r i and f m r i does not inject anything
into the body so the invasiveness is low but
here the purchase causes very high because
the kind of magnets that the m r i and f m
r i uses are huge electromagnets and they
have huge ah amount of cost involved into
them
the last method that we use here is called
the optical imaging method and here this is
a recent addition so it has been found out
that the brain is transparent to certain kind
of ah light waves and when these light waves
are shown into the brain through a through
a laser the speed with which they return back
can give you an idea of how much blood is
flowing through that particular area and so
this can be used this method is now being
used to find out the amount of blood travelling
through a particular area depending on how
much ah light laser light is being reflected
back through ah various tissues and and various
substances in in the brain
it is the special resolution at present is
very poor and the ah temporal resolution it
depends on the level of resolution and several
minutes takes up from forming an image the
invasiveness is generally ah medium to low
as lasers are ah shown on to or lo lasers
are focused on to your brain so it has some
level of an invasiveness but not too high
the cost of purchase is very low but the temporal
relation is not appropriate
one of the examples of f m r i which is ah
ah functional ah optical imaging ah suit which
is available these days another method of
studying cognition is through using the causal
neural method of studying cognition what does
this method do in this method it is assumed
that if certain regions of the brain are required
for certain activity what would happen if
that vision of the brain is somehow not allowed
to do any activity or stops from doing activity
and so one of the ah one of the particular
ah methods within this approach is using patience
who have certain brain damage
so suppose the broca area is responsible for
speech and so if somebody has a deficit in
the broca area and if certain type of speech
related experiments are given to ah to them
and compared to a particular normal ah ah
person it would be easy to understand what
kind of what kind of activity does the brain
does what is requirement of this area and
so on and so forth so here in this in the
neurophysiological studies patients with localized
brain damage or brain damage to certain areas
are used and they compared with people who
have no brain damage and this is how the cognitive
processes or the mental processes that go
on when a particular mental activity is being
done is actually studied
example could be deficit in understanding
the how nouns and verbs are processed and
so people who have deficit in this area if
you give them a noun and a verb the area since
it is deficit so now it will show no activity
whereas people who do not have deficits will
show different activity and so that will be
enough to say that this area is responsible
for a particular kind of act that is being
required the advantages is of this method
is testing theories of causal role of specific
brain areas testing theories of shad in distinct
processing and used in different task relatively
easy and inexpensive to collect
the limitation is we do not find too many
people who have damaged areas and so the idea
is its its very difficult to ah find people
with damage areas also when damage to a particular
area is there there will be ah related areas
which might be affected by the damage so it
is very difficult to localize whether the
this damage is to this area or which this
is damage the damaged brain area also has
any relation with other areas
the second method in this particular group
is called the transcranial magnetic stimulation
now in t m s there are two types of t m s
s one is called the single pulse and the other
is called the repeated t m s or the repeated
trans ah pulse may trans transcranial magnetic
stimulation what really happens here it ha
is that a huge coil is put into a near or
on the surface of an area to temporarily inhabit
and a large current is passed through this
coil
the magnetic field that is generated by this
coil temporarily inhabits a particular area
and through through that we can find out whether
the disrupt how what will happen if a particular
area which is known to be associated with
a particular ah activity cognitive activity
if it is disrupted what really happens so
what we could or ah studies of how visual
imagery is different from perception can be
done by using t m s t m s or using a r t m
s and blocking the occipital lobe
now there is a difference between single pulse
t m s and r t m s in single pulse t m s a
single pulse is given after the stimulus is
is is generated and the time course of this
pulse is recorded and that gives us an idea
of how the or what activity is happening in
that area
whereas in r t m s repeated pulses are given
over a particular area so that these weak
pulses they add up together to inhabit a particular
area the inhabition happens because the neurons
under that area becomes too fa too ah too
extended they they fired so many times that
they they ah go through a phase of non firing
and that inhabits the area or that that depolarization
inhabits that area activity in that area
so advantages it is it has the same advantage
as the neurophysiological studies but here
the lesions are restricted and also the idea
here is that in these regions in in in the
t m s the disruption is for a very beu brief
period of time and so patients can come out
out of it or subjects can come out of it
also t m s s can be done for surface areas
it cannot be done for deep areas of the brain
ah and so it is one of the disadvantage on
limitation of this particular method another
method which can relate or which can show
how a particular brain area disrupting or
particular brain area has effects on the particular
mental process is using specific drugs so
here what happens is first a pa particular
drug is specifically used and these drugs
inhabit a particular area of interest and
so once this area of interest is inhabited
the same task is given to a person who has
taken this drug which inhabits area and a
person who has not had drugs which inhabits
this area and comparisons are made
these comparisons give us an idea of what
really happens or how mental processes what
brain areas are involved what mental processes
is being processed and what is the time course
of process of this ah mental events
the problem ah example was disruption of disruptive
action of not adrenal in which is crucial
for the operation of hippocampus non adrenal
injection is given to the hippocampus and
though hippocampus actually becomes temporally
disturbed and so when you give a memory task
to this person he will not be able to process
this memory task and not come up with ah ah
the better of how ah or the particularly travel
paradigm in comparison to somebody who has
no disruptions and this will show how much
or to what extent does which part of hippocampus
relates to a particular memory type
drugs when used to inhabit a particular area
effects not only the area of interest but
also effects other area which is related to
this area and so this effect can also be ah
ah can can can can be generalized to other
areas similar similar to this effect the t
m s also has this particular disadvantage
where activation of a particular area can
lead to activation of subsequent areas and
so what would happen is the disruption will
not be in that particular area but also move
out or generalize to other areas of brain
and so to stay with confidence that this is
this disruption of this area is responsible
for particular mental act is becomes a little
bit dicey
also the limitation is that many drugs can
create many other ah problem and so this is
this has to be used under supervision the
last method that we discussed here of studying
cognition or cognitive psychology is using
modeling
so in psychology models are implemented as
computer programs which are meant to be make
the underlying mental representation and processes
that produces different specific types of
human performances so generally models are
made and this models try and explain the different
processes events that actually happen when
a particular ah mental event or a particular
ah cognition happens there are two types of
models which are studied in cognitive psychology
one of these is the process model and the
second is the neural network model so what
is the process model
the process model specifies the sequence of
processes that converts an input into output
and can these kind of processes can be used
to generate flow charts so basically its it
is a box diagram kind of a thing where you
get from one pa one phase to another one event
to another event and the processes which relate
these events together
coming back to understanding the process model
let us recall the structure process trade
off that we saw in the last class and so in
the last class and so in the last class steinbergs
example in which what he did was he he wanted
to study the mental process of how comparisons
are made in in the ah comparisons are made
in cognition and so what he did was he gave
his subjects a particular number of items
to remember and then these items were tested
the retrieval of this the memory for this
item were tested through a probe and what
steinberg proposed is that this search for
the target in the list of item that is being
studied or the that is being remembered happens
through a serial process
generally speaking this idea that a serial
process look through a list of items which
administrate in memory can be explained through
a process model and this is the process model
which explains how this serial processing
takes place
so generally how this experiment would work
is when a probe is given the probe is first
encoded prior to this people are given a list
to remember and the list has several numbers
or several letters into it and what the job
is the subjects look at a probe and then found
out whether this probe is present in this
list or not and to explain this process a
process model can be developed how will the
process model really works look at this in
finding out or scanning whether the probe
is present in the list which is remembered
the first step is encoding of the probe this
is followed by scanning and comparing where
processes internal processes take the probe
and match it with each item which is represented
which is stored into the the memory for each
item after a comparison a decision has to
be made
so let us say this if we have one two three
four and five stored list of items stored
or five numbers stored in a memory and if
you want to compare whether three is present
or not how this model will really work or
how this process with really work in terms
of mental effect is that three is first encoded
later on three is matched scanned and compared
with the fist item this which is one and so
a decision has to be made here whether one
is three or not since both the representations
for three and one are different ah response
has to be executed here the response is no
and the process moves to the second item
now three is take it in compared with two
since both the representations are different
ah response here has to be generated which
says the three is not equal to two and so
we do not find a match and we move to the
third item which is three now here three and
three had the same representations and so
we get a yes response make a decision the
yes response comes in and so in terms of serial
processing the process does not stop here
it continues continues to the end of the list
and then gives the final answer so that is
how the process model explains the process
model ex actually goes ahead and explains
how this simple job or simple task of comparing
a probe with the list which has been already
remembered actually goes ahead
the problem with this process model is it
tells you about the processes that goes through
or the processes that happen when this list
comparison or probe list testing is done but
it does not tell you how does the brain or
what neural factors play role into this particular
whole structure so this has this is basically
this kind of process models are basically
influenced by the behaviors which believe
that the input output sequence is what is
of important to us but what is inside is not
of importance to us
and so it does not give you the brain structures
the brain processes which actually go ahead
and lead to the fa final answer of comparisons
or final comparisons that are done and so
to counter that neural network models were
done or thought of now what are the neural
ma network model it relies on interconnected
units which has not just input output units
but it has a hidden hidden unit which is generally
called the brain unit into it and so most
inputs are connected to a hidden unit and
the hidden unit are further connected to an
output unit so if i encoding ah if a input
unit is given this input unit then goes ahead
and makes connections with this hidden units
which are generally neurons
now this type of ah ah neural network structure
that i am showing you is a simple feed forward
network what happens here is there are three
units l one l two and three three which inputs
which have been taken and these inputs are
then compared or then processed through h
one h two h three three different brain ah
networks or neuronal networks now each of
this network can have only two activity one
is either it can be excitatory which is the
i response or inhibitory of response
so when a particular input a particular representation
from the environment is encoded this particular
network or this particular respon ah neuronal
network will either be excitatory will either
passed along with either move along this information
to the next network and show a connection
or it could show inhibitory whereas it will
not ah process this information further
also these connections that the input layer
or the input item has with the hidden layer
has weights into it and depending on what
weight it is what is the strength of this
connection will decide whether this inhab
whether this response of excitation or inhibition
will these ah will this hidden units actually
show and based on the excitatory or inhibitory
input or mode of the hidden layer and the
weights of the input layer the output layer
is finally or the outputs are finally determined
and so that is how we see that l one or i
one represents gives to give rise to o two
and the hidden layer the neural network or
the group of neurons which actually process
it how does it really function
so this particular model shows us gives us
several ah benefit for example it it it shows
us what are the neural codes which are there
which are which are ah which are responsible
for this kind of an output and it distinguishes
this neural codes for mental representations
so it does not just tell you mental representation
of how a event is represented in in memory
but also what are the brain states or what
are the neuron of the states which are processing
this particular neuronal unit
so that brings us to the end of this session
and to do a quick recap in this session what
we did was we looked at the different methods
of studying cognition and we looked at the
heart of this ah study the use of different
methods that the the basic point being that
as we use different methods we get several
whatever the ah the loophole from one method
turns out to be the benefit from another method
and so we get a more comprehensive picture
if one method explains process a but cannot
explain process b may be there is another
method which can explain process b and ah
comes up with another limitations and so looking
at the benefits and limitations of all these
methods give us a more complete picture of
how cognitive or cognitive processes develop
and so within that we looked at four different
types of ah methods or four different ah techniques
of studying cognition right from behavioral
techniques where we look at accuracy response
time judgments and protocol to coming up ah
with techniques which actually go ahead and
localize or pinpoint a br brain area which
is active when a particular mental process
is being carried out and ah the methods like
e e g p e t m m r i or f m r i and optical
imaging to looking at ca casual methods which
actually disrupt a brain area which is believed
to be active when a particular event is being
taking place or ventricular mental event is
being taking place to the methods of ah modeling
where ah a process is designed a computer
stimulation is designed which mimics what
the brain does
so instead of studying the brain itself um
um a mimic or a model of that is done and
studied in a through computer stimulations
to find out ah what will happen if a particular
input or a particular group of brains ah brain
areas ah which which are known to respond
in particular ways if they take in an information
how what is the possible output that can come
in
thank you